Hypertext Markup Language, or HTML, is a language
that defines the structure of content on a
web page.
Development started in 1989 at SERN by Tim
Berners-Lee, who had just invented the world's
first web browser, World Wide Web, the origin
of www.
But he needed a publishing language to display
content within it, so he chose a syntax
based on the standard generalized markup language, which
uses opening and closing tags to provide meaning
to otherwise unorganized text, like h for heading,
p for paragraph, and most importantly, a for
anchor to link to a different web page.
The language underwent many changes during the initial
rise of the internet and was standardized as
HTML5 in 2008, the version we know and
love today.
Modern HTML contains tags to handle a variety
of different media types, like video, audio, and
canvas to draw custom graphics on the fly.
The typical HTML element starts with an opening
and closing tag.
In the middle, we have content, which might
be text, or additional HTML elements called children.
The opening tag may also have one or
more attributes, which are key value pairs that
can customize the appearance or behavior of the
element.
To build your first web page, create a
file named index.html. This file contains a
hierarchy of nodes based on the document object
model, or DOM.
A web page starts with an HTML tag
and has exactly two children, a head and
a body.
The head contains things that aren't directly shown
in the web page, like a title or
a meta tag, to give the page a
description.
But notice how the meta element has no
closing tag.
Closing tags are generally optional when an element
is fully self-contained.
The body contains the actual UI for the
end user.
We might start with an h1 heading, followed
by a paragraph of content.
To add an image, we use an image
tag, which you'll notice is self-closing.
Then define the source attribute as the file
path to the image, and you'll want to
give it an old description to make it
accessible to robots and screen readers.
What makes web pages revolutionary, though, is their
ability to link to other web pages on
the information superhighway.
Use an anchor tag to create a link,
then define the href attribute as the web
page that you want to navigate to when
clicked.
HTML also provides structural tags like division or
div, which are often used to group elements
together, where they can be styled to represent
complex UI elements like navbars.
When you're happy with your code, grab the
full file path to the HTML file and
paste it into any web browser.
Congratulations, you just built your first website!
This has been Hypertext Markup Language in 100
seconds.
Hit the subscribe button so you don't miss
the upcoming sequels.
Thanks for watching, and I will see you
in the next one.